this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello this is Kishore patia for
software engineering video today's
episode is about blockchain with Kieran
James Lubin Kieran is the co-founder of
block apps a PhD candidate at Berklee
researching mathematical physics
interested in data science and block
genes he's also on the Technical Working
Group at the etherium Enterprise
Alliance as an engineering leader at
block apps I work closely with Kieran
welcome to software engineering radio
Keene thanks for having me today we are
going to talk about block chains and
specifically cover etherium block chain
protocol and smart contracts so Kieran
what is a block chain in its most basic
form it's an excellent question
in its most basic form a block chain is
simply a record or a ledger which is
append-only
which records transactions of some kind
these these transactions could have a
monetary implication or they could be
representing you know the advancement of
a state of some sort of business process
and the unique feature the block chains
provide beyond traditional databases or
you know pieces of paper that are penned
only is that this this ledger can be
agreed upon by you know multiple
counterparties without a central
clearinghouse so in comparison to to our
current system in which we have many
clearing houses which exists more or
less to establish the truth blockchain
technology in and of itself can
establish the the golden record of who
is holding what when interesting yeah
so you mentioned distributed ledger here
and the fact that you can have a coded
copy agreed upon by many parties would
you want would you dive in a little bit
in in that certainly certainly so the
first application of blockchain
technology was Bitcoin and it was sort
of the origin of the idea what
has a larger implication in my opinion
so what what bitcoin achieved was a
fully peer-to-peer currency and you know
the important aspect of a currency you
know if we think about paying each other
cash it's that that you know cash is not
really counterfeit able and that when it
changes hands it really changes hands
which is easy to imagine in the physical
world but in the software world you know
we struggle to make digital content
scarce in some sense you know it's it's
very easy to duplicate bits and yet you
know US dollars are not meant to be
counterfeited so what what bitcoin
achieved is having a peer-to-peer
digital currency using the underlying
watching technology for for the value
transfer use case so basically the way
this manifests is that given that you
know there are transactions are in
Bitcoin are gonna be you know I send ten
Bitcoin dickish or the the problem that
needs resolving is what if I also send
ten Bitcoin to someone else and those
are the only ten Bitcoin that I have how
do we decide who actually gets the
Bitcoin and we previously believed that
really only a centralized system could
could handle reconciling between those
two transactions they decide you know
which transaction occurred first and
that's the record but Bitcoin actually
has proven that through its consensus
algorithm that it's possible for a
peer-to-peer network to decide you know
which transaction happened first and
which one is the authentic one I see
yeah that's pretty interesting you
mentioned a couple of terms here around
peer-to-peer value transfer digital
representation of the de currency and
the fact that these peers are actually
running a consensus algorithm we should
dive in a bit on all of these but to
begin with covering these topics how do
you describe achieving you know such a
distributed consensus within a
blockchain network let me describe I
guess the experience of joining a
network like Bitcoin
if they're in and that might be helpful
so one downloads you know a piece of
software that people tend to call a
client like a blockchain client in a
sense it's not a client-server
architecture but it's a client of the
network so to speak and someone
downloads this piece of software and
what the software does is basically
download all of history after joining
the peer-to-peer now so the client will
know a few entry points to the network
and can find peers through these entry
points and the peers will transfer the
history of the system to to the client
that's maybe on my laptop so that I can
verify all the current you know state of
all the balances in the system so that
that process occurs I could if I like to
start broadcasting transactions before
I'm in sync but it's better to know that
I'm in sync with the network before I
start doing that and the way that the
software can tell that the data is
authentic is actually in the case of the
public Bitcoin network due to the
consensus algorithm known as mining
essentially so what mining is is
basically at each I think they're called
blocks block in blockchain in each block
which block consists of a bundle of
transactions you know say value transfer
transactions and some metadata and the
metadata is a reference to the parent
block which establishes the order of the
system and some data that sort of proves
that the block required some
computational expenditure to create and
this this uses cryptographic hash
functions basically what the property of
that metadata is that someone you know
burned compute on their laptop on their
GPU and their data center to produce
this block and it has a unique kind of
information theoretically unlikely
fingerprint which proves that they they
spent the money on it and so that that X
is sort of a truth mechanism and also a
rate limiting mechanism for the open
peer-to-peer network so in practice it
take
on the Bitcoin network about a
ten-minute interval to produce a block
and transactions are not confirmed until
they appear in a valid block and really
you should wait a few blocks before you
consider transactions confirmed and so
this mechanism allows a network with an
arbitrary number of participants to
establish the truth and also when I join
it later it's a it's efficient to verify
that this network is the truthful
network because the most compute power
has been spent on it and that's a thing
that you can check as you're downloading
history so that's a technical answer but
but the key components are that the data
itself is verifiable and it's verifiable
for a real-world
expenditure proving that the the order
of the system the order of the blocks in
the system and the data is authentic
right yeah so if I understand correctly
we're talking about distributor system
pretty much three centralized no central
authority or a single system making a
decision and in controlling the source
of truth but every peer in that network
has an exact copy of the number of
transactions that have happened in a
particular sequence and that is
deterministic and you can get you know
you can get a complete view of the
pillager how is that actually you know
achieved in in a system where you know
people can't just trust these these
machines you know running all over the
world over you know over the Internet so
I'm trying to dive into the the trust
aspect of it how how do you how do you
trust such a network
well yeah there's a technical answer and
a philosophical answer I suppose I think
the technical answer is that what you
can tell from the network is what people
spent their their money on in terms of
the mining process so it's sort of not
majority vote it's not you know the it's
not captured by a single counterparty
but rather the its its vote by CPU
essentially so the people that spend the
most energy and the most on Hardware on
deciding what the canonical history is
are the the ones that determine the
truth so those people are also
incentivized to and they're incentivized
in terms of the issuance of the token so
Bitcoin etherium and their public forum
only issue new tokens essentially by
this mining process and so when you you
know when you win a block right there's
actually a reward that you can send to
an address of your choice likely one
that you can control and that functions
as an incentive to align with the
correctness of the blockchain network
itself and so those those that are
producing these blocks are again aligned
with the sort of future of the protocol
so to speak and so maybe that's the
definition of trust correctness that
we're talking about so you know in the
in a traditional IT environment Trust is
more of a PKI certificate authority kind
of perspective that you know you know
who everyone is what they're doing and
in there's sort of an honored log of
everything that a particular person does
and this technology achieves similar
ends though through a different
mechanism of of having a trust-based or
trust list depending on your perspective
system without you know needing to know
all the individual identities I see and
for the listeners PKI is public key
infrastructure
ciarán what do you want diving in a
little bit in establishing that trust
over these publicly exposed networks
using certain you know secure mechanisms
like public keys and the fact that
someone putting information on such a
decentralized system can actually you
know see some use cases not just
currency but other information sharing
use cases so from a technical
perspective joining this network I mean
it's an open and peer-to-peer network
and so you always have to be careful to
lock down the appropriate ports and you
know as you you're opening ports to go
connect to the spirit of your network
you know there is some concern about
what kind of payload from a data
perspective that could land on your
machine in in the case of a Bitcoin or
aetherium the the wire protocol is
pretty constrained so that you know it's
it's hard for anyone to send something
that you're not expecting and if you do
you certainly don't just execute it on
your your native machine so less of a
concern there but it is an open Internet
Protocol I mean the the intent is that
anyone can join the network in you know
five ten thousand people will be active
on each of the Bitcoin the etherium
Network set and they give an instant and
you may not know they are they may be
connecting with proxies this that and
the other and that doesn't affect the
security of the the core ledger in that
it's not an individual trust based
system but rather a sort of vote by CPU
system so what has been and still is
driving these notions and demands for
these centralized systems yeah so I
think there are so several movements
that that are going on I think the the
expectation on behalf of consumers is
kind of going in in two directions one
consumers want sort of personalized
technology they want to you know own and
manage their own data they're they're
more sort of personal eccentric people
don't want to go show up to their bank
they want to you know use some kind of
online interface and then have it figure
out what they want
so this there's that one track but also
we're actually more comfortable with you
know connecting to the world just
through the internet and you know less
less in person and so so now all of our
data is moving to big companies like
Google Amazon and whatnot despite having
a stronger individualistic desire to
manage it and so the technology in
itself is a bit of an attack on these
sort of centralized data clearing houses
that we have you can find them anywhere
I mean most software applications are
delivered in a client-server manner and
your data resides with some some
corporate and so the philosophical roots
of Bitcoin which is you know the root of
the blockchain technology itself
definitely in a movement called crypto
anarchism which I believe began you know
as early as the late 80s early 90s and
you know Bitcoin was one of the first
large realized initiatives of the sort
of cyberpunk crypto anarchist groups and
you know what it is is a is a currency
that's not controlled by the government
or that sort of thing so that is kind of
one of the the philosophical origins of
the technology I would say and in the
United States you know our financial
systems work quite well we can grumble a
little bit but they're not especially
high cost and they're fairly efficient
in certain other countries where you
have hyperinflation or capital controls
or this that and the other
the demand for cryptocurrency or digital
currency is probably higher in that you
know people see it as a vehicle to
protect their their assets their wealth
etc and really in the US consumer
experience you know it coin aetherium
whatnot are not all that prevalent but
and in other countries you know paying
what bitcoin is actually sort of
extremely common so you know I think
it's it's sort of indicative of a
general movement to towards individual
centric sovereignty experience of
products etc that was rooted in sort of
a somewhat extreme crypto anarchist
philosophy to start but has sort of made
its way into the mainstream and so far I
see so if I understand it right the
history and the roots of this movement
and what also got created as a
blockchain technology is a lot driven by
individuals people wanting control of
their privacy their data and also the
fact that the digital world as we get
more and more connected you know would
have all of that data available in these
big data stores off of you know banks
and corporate walls and people want that
that control you you called crypto
anarchism could you throw some more
light on that that history and yes well
certainly not an expert there for free
listeners out there but basically the
the movement I think one of the the key
figures is - Tim May I think he broke in
original manifesto that you know
basically the the idea is that we as
people could interact mostly through
machines this means you know everything
from your day-to-day to corporate
governance to you know to currency to
this that in the other and further in
some sense not have our traditional
governance institutions in place be they
that the federal government or you know
institutions that we rely on to achieve
what we need to achieve on the in the
day-to-day but rather that this could
all be software that we individually can
run individually can control so you know
there's sort of there is a obviously an
anarchist aspect to it there's also a
bit of a pie-in-the-sky aspect to it as
well but you know with with Bitcoin some
of this has been in theory achieved now
whether it's sort of in practice
achieved from a consumer convenience
perspective I would question but I think
that that is the route at least so far
as I know of the the people who
we're working on Bitcoin before its
launch who have never been officially
identified but the the technology in
itself has a strong sort of
philosophical roots that are that are
well documented as being in part by
tourists is Bitcoin
the only big example of how the
blockchain revolution began or like how
would you establish the theory of
blockchains
in the real digital world outside of the
cryptocurrency revolution yeah it was an
interesting point so I think Bitcoin
first launched sometime in 2009 and it
was sort of the sole blockchain and
cryptocurrency for some period of time
it was open source so people made many
derivative versions of Bitcoin with sort
of varied parameters minor changes to
the core that so that there's something
like a thousand or more Bitcoin
derivative currencies out there so that
happened sort of relatively quickly to
the next really major event especially
with respect to public blockchains was
the etherium white paper was written
November 2013 I believe by Vitalik
butyrin so at the time an eighteen year
old you know
von der Kent if you will who was very
very mathematically precocious he was a
student at the University of Waterloo
Canada's best Technical University and
that's so interested in Bitcoin he also
covered it from a journalistic
perspective that he started quite
actively working on projects in the
Bitcoin space then found that you know
these these projects were difficult to
execute on Bitcoin because basically the
core protocol was very hard to extend
and people were building sort of the
spoke single use case Bitcoin derivative
block chains and not you know leveraging
a general-purpose system in which one
blockchain could have you know multiple
applications and so that was sort of the
core idea of atheria and so the etherium
projects you know look looking forward
the actual public blockchain launched I
believe in July of 2015 and heading into
that time we also saw you know huge
growth in corporate interest in in
blockchains so large Manx large oil and
gas companies large retailers large
manufacturers are now seeing that the
problems that are solved in the public
watch and space are still present in in
a corporate context in which you know
there are many thousands tens of
thousands of parties within a supply
chain for instance and they have a hard
time deciding you know a unique record
of which goods were shipped to whom when
just as Bitcoin resolves the the unique
record of value transfers from whom at
what time in which order so the the the
technology is is growing and the the
public understanding of its
applicability and the definition also is
is expanding to really any system that
is is a peer-to-peer system of record in
which participants can join later and
verify the history and continue to
participate on a go-forward I would call
that a blockchain so in my opinion the
the public network ISM which has mining
for instance as a consensus algorithm
that's not the only use case or not the
only definition of up watching this is
really helpful I think we definitely
covered a lot of the converging concepts
that give an evolutionary concept like
blockchain a big Trust beginning with
you know crypto anarchism crypto
currencies trust and the decentralized
world you mentioned you know a couple
things mostly around the use cases
evolving now in the in the enterprise
world outside of the crypto currency we
definitely want to dive more with
aetherium on that but let's just first
cover the some of the main concepts that
you you know we want to actually
understand of what
work comprises a blockchain Network what
are the cool technologies that one has
to understand as a software engineer to
start making sense of a you know a
blockchain Network what would you say
are the you know some some of the things
that one would have to learn or have
experience in in order to interpret some
of the things that create a block King
yeah that's a good question and it
depends sort of that what level one is
engaging from an application developer
perspective one only really needs to
understand kind of something about the
the core blockchain data model and then
some set of API is to interact with it
to post new transactions to read
historical transactions to load the
state of the blockchain at the given
point in time etc that is you know
getting to be a fairly solved problem in
that you know a pretty good web
developer can build blotching
applications fairly easily right now
from an operational perspective that one
has to sort of understand were the
networking technologies so locked hands
again they're peer-to-peer networks in
which there's communication and the
communication is usually the broadcast
of particular transactions so there's
also an identity management aspect
transactions in the blockchain world are
sort of cryptographically signed
messages from particular you know public
keys essentially so the the only way in
a theorem world in the Bitcoin world
that value transfer occurs is that again
a transaction which is a cryptically
signed message is appended to the ledger
and that is the definition of you know
value movement so to speak and so one
has to have that understanding in one
you know as long as planning one's IT
infrastructure and then you know one has
to think about how this how the
management of those keys would occur are
the keys with the participants are they
in a server somewhere you know are they
using secure hardware and whatnot how's
the you know how's the network monitored
how are the particular nodes in the
network
I'll check for health checked for
consistency and so on
and you know this in in a public network
scenario this is more something that you
would check on your laptop but for an
enterprise use case they're still you
know quite heavy traditional enterprise
IT requirements to participate in
blockchain network which are somewhat
different than traditional IT
infrastructure
this podcast is supported by atlanticnet
hosting solution provider of healthcare
HIPAA PCI compliance and ad tech if
you're feeling the pain of having
outdated technology call atlanticnet and
get the latest security firewall
intrusion detection backup disaster
recovery and virtualization or if you're
starting a new project are not getting
the results you want from your current
providers atlanticnet can help you
succeed with fully audited solutions in
23 years in business they won't let you
down
visit atlanticnet to learn more
[Music]
so just to recap you mentioned based on
the experience level and you know the
area that you're involved in with
blockchains there's a lot going on with
the experience and you know networking
peer-to-peer messaging protocols
there's also Identity Management with
the ability to understand you know
cryptographic keys encryption decryption
at the node level at the individual
level there's this concept of databases
or data stores that you know come in
mostly aligned to the distributed ledger
aspect of the block chains and then the
systems at scale for IT where how do you
actually you know run and maintain and
operate a large distributed system at
scale but that's really helpful on the
on the other hand you mentioned if
helium is basically picking up as one of
the next frontiers for blockchains
mostly also diving into the enterprise
aspect of it can you throw some more
light on what is it helium covered some
of the basic foundational concepts there
certainly so if theorem is a technology
and it's a protocol one thing that's
sort of maybe not broadly understood
about a theorem is that there's a spec
and definition for this protocol it's
it's like HTTP so many people anyone can
go and implement a version of aetherium
if they if they so choose so aetherium
is also a public blockchain and so what
that means is as I described before one
can download a clients and aetherium
client connect to a peer-to-peer network
download the history and then start to
broadcast transactions in you know
validate new transactions on a
go-forward basis so the unique feature
of aetherium against something like a
Bitcoin or you know any of bitcoins
derivatives is that it's a more
computationally rich execution
environment so again in Bitcoin supports
basically the use case of value transfer
and a little bit more you can have bad
metadata in transactions and sometimes
interpret that metadata in the real
world and so that can describe some sort
of derived asset
rather than just a Bitcoin could it
could be that you know a transaction
means that some real-world asset
transfer of say a physical good even has
has happened and that's about the limit
so what aetherium adds are smart
contracts and the smart contracts
basically achieve is the ability to
model more complex workflows than you
can with the technology like Bitcoin so
if you can imagine a complex business
process like settlement of a security
for instance as a popular a use case in
financial services you know when when we
talk to some of our customers about how
these settlement processes occur they're
not really very simple they're
long-running there's many steps which
can often be modeled as sort of a large
multi tenant state machine and that's
essentially kind of where the etherium
is that many parties can interact with a
smart contract or set of smart contracts
which represent the state of a business
process and at a sort of permissioned
level can carry out that process to to
its conclusion all on the same you know
shared system of record interesting so
ethelia offers if i'm synchronously
a way to embed code with some levels of
storage and and a permanent contract on
the chain establishing you know a level
of agreement between parties that are
making that contract is that right and
can be type into an example of that
maybe in the the supply chain world as
you mentioned earlier I would say that
is accurate the the smart contracts
don't necessarily have to represent a
legal agreement really their their
software objects but they can certainly
represent a legal agreement but then
there's some question of you know which
is the truth the legal agreement or the
contract itself which I think our
societies have not quite resolved but
but yes certainly so as an example one
of our production systems the large
mining company and basically the smart
contract entities there are many of them
but
are basically representing kind of raw
materials and their motion through the
supply chain so these raw materials are
mined then they're sent to one of
potentially hundreds of you know vendors
which are sort of engineering companies
which do analyses to these to these
samples and the provenance is very
important and so it's it's a regulated
process and each action that's done to
the sample is sort of a regulatory event
in substance and so there are sort of
PDFs that get produced that are kind of
attached to the sample and sort of just
as valuable as the sample itself and you
know what the blockchain is achieving is
is sort of creating a unique record of
the provenance of the sample as it goes
across many different corporations and
then as eventually you know ends its
life and it ends its life by being
stored with the government so in that
case the the workflow is somewhat
complex you know the samples are first
mined really their first procured by
central office user then their mind and
then so that's a state advance then once
they've in mind they are ready to ship
to a vendor in the office selects which
vendor to ship to and then they're in
transit and then that the the vendor
that can claim the samples and only that
vendor can claim the samples that's
actually checked at a cryptographic
level and so the samples are sort of
imported so to speak in you know as
they've been received then the that that
vendor can do analysis to them which is
a you know involves the addition of some
some metadata to the samples history and
then the vendor will either ship the
sample to another vendor or ship it to
be stored so you know somewhat complex
business process there and would be you
know a difficult thing to do without the
smart contract facility which is kind of
coordinating this this complex workflow
I see interesting how smart contracts
have been used here what
you so what are these smart contracts
developed in like is there a specific
language to develop them yeah that's a
good question
so the standard today basically is a
language in the etherium world
that the language is called solidity and
solidity is sort of this javascript c
style syntax and it is compiled language
actually compiles down to the etherium
byte code theory and as a virtual sort
of a stack based virtual machine has its
execution engine and so the smart
contracts are compiled to this this
language and you know some it's a fairly
easy thing to get up and running with so
if you look into solidity viewers out
there or listeners out there that you
can kind of get started some of the the
positive features of solidity versus you
know a traditional programming language
where that you might have encountered
you know there's always the question why
not write this more context and a
traditional programming languages that
solidity ensures that transactions are
deterministic and so you know if you if
you make a call to the system time and
say a language like go Java or whatever
you know that won't necessarily have the
same result at different physical
locations in the world on different
computers and so on and so that starts
to break some of the value proposition
of watching technology if you lose
determinism then all you have is an
ordered set of transactions and they may
have different meanings to different
people so you really want this
determinism property so solidity is sort
of a nice object-oriented language which
has the determinant property it's sort
of like the smart contracts are more or
less like small talk objects and you
validity is a good way to actually get
started with writing smart contracts on
it cerium that also differentiates the
tedium from the previous you know
implementations like Bitcoin for a
blockchain based system can we dive in a
little bit into what kind of tools or
testing libraries are available for you
know a developer to to start writing
smart contracts and testing them it also
we we want to understand for our
listeners how they can start you know
with way to developing smart contracts
certainly so there's a variety of open
source tools available to start
prototyping smart contracts so the if
you just search for solidity you'll find
lots of them so also a plug for my
company so so block apps we distribute
the developer edition of our software
which has JavaScript SDKs for slow dates
really aimed at the web developer so you
can just download this at you know it
requires docker and nothing else comes
up and running and you could start
uploading and interacting with solidity
contracts right away there are also
other tools truffle is a popular tool
for prototyping smart contracts and you
know if you download any of the etherium
code bases there's a bit of
configuration to do if you don't use our
stuff but you can start interacting with
smart contracts from a testing
perspective there and what what's
usually done is you know setting up a
test suite likely and in javascript that
you know deploys the smart contracts and
then runs their particular functions and
checks that the result is what you
expect I see that's pretty interesting
the use of the different tools and and
testing libraries would help the
ecosystem evolve as well and get more
and more developers excited about it I
will put in the the links in the podcast
notes for the white paper the solidity
language and also the tools
in in the stock so Kyra moving on to the
areas and the problems that we are
solving what do you see in the in your
company in block apps specifically as
you know areas of focus that that you
are constantly evolving in and
developing on right and for the
listeners maybe some context you would
be useful so block UPS is a b2b
enterprise focused company and our
mission is to take the core technology
that blockchain represents particularly
in the etherium variant and make it
consumable for enterprises sort of large
and small and so enterprises of
different requirements and many cannot
engage with the public networking part
because of the level of control over it
from a governance perspective in part
because of how visible the data on it is
and so we have taken really the the
exact same core technology but added
certain features that enterprises need
to be able to derive some of the same
benefits that the public network has so
our focus in terms of you know say
customer base but also you know on a
roadmap perspective we're about 40 50
percent working with financial services
customers in in neighboring industries
we have some insurance and that sort of
thing as well and then some 50 percent
of the rest and the rest is is leaning
heavily into supply chain management use
cases so you know big oil and gas mining
but also heavy manufacturing companies
with that high very high value inventory
consumer packaged goods in which you
know showing the authenticity of the
food we eat is a really important thing
major retailers etc are all interested
in you know logistics optimization and
traceability which is something that the
technology can provide
interesting you mentioned a couple use
cases in supply chain you know also the
the natural resources energy mining
company example that you gave before and
then another good one around the food
the farm table could you go in and
provide an example for the the founder
table of provenance you know and how
blockchains can help there certainly
certainly so so there's this tremendous
all-around interest in farm-to-table
provenance of goods and the goods can
have could be of any kind you know one
example is just food one another example
would be say in the u.s. we have export
rules around which sort of technologies
can be sold to other countries
especially in the defense industry and
so a use case we we've heard is that one
really has to know if one is is
depending on any components that might
have you know regulated export basically
and that it's it's difficult in some
cases to know if you're building a
complex a machine may be with hundreds
of thousands millions of parts that all
of them have the origin that you expect
and so they're the functions used as a
ledger for basically the whole supply
chain and all the participants in the
supply chain have an identity on the
blockchain so the lifecycle of a good
can as it knows you know as constituent
components are assembled as physical
components is to say raw materials to
you know somewhat processed materials to
smaller packaged goods to to larger
goods that whole history is present and
auditable and so the technology allows
something that hasn't existed basically
the previously the systems of record of
all the entities in the supply chain
were not linked in any way and so while
there would be one good one couldn't go
back and figure out you know all the
hops that it that the constituent
components have made in their lifetimes
so speak nicely the technology itself
can establish that multi you know multi
corporate multi-tenant golden record for
what
it actually is interesting yeah
and meanwhile there are a lot of you
know blockchain use cases that are
coming up to kind of compare it with the
distributed databases and central data
stores of the world that have already
been established in some of the
industries what would you say for a lot
of you know the use cases that are being
thrown out blockchains
where they don't initially seem like or
even are specific to block genes is
there a specific use case or mechanism
that you have seen to validate some some
of these use cases sure a couple
questions and better there one one
suggestion that I'd make is to not view
the technology as a database replacement
while it is a data store and house
database properties it's not necessarily
optimized for that particular use case I
think of blockchains more is a kind of
coordination workflow data integration
and collaboration tool so that watchings
are actually just a safe way for you
know many parties to collaborate on a
single source of record that can be
transparently synchronized across those
those parties and so you do get
differentiated value with the technology
really when there's more than one party
and you know that could mean in some
cases we you know there are
multinationals that that have different
subsidiaries or branches if you will and
those can behave as sort of different
legal entities so in some cases that
even a single corporation can derive
benefit from deploying the technology
but where the technology is really
differentiated is when there are complex
multi corporate or multi multi sincerely
multi tenant business processes that
suffer for not having a unique golden
record and one way to detect those use
cases is to look for the presence of
clearing houses so you have the the
financial services the exchanges will
have some clearing capacity there's the
Federal Reserve with ACH is the
Depository Trust & Clearing Corporation
on
all looking at the technology because in
a sense it achieves part of what their
institutions achieve which is to
establish kind of the golden record of
of the truth of you know of what belongs
to whom
but you also see see clearing houses in
other industries like you know airline
hotels a hospitality bookings actually
is very complex reconciliation processes
that are powered by global distribution
systems that again have more or less the
same function so that's a good the
guideline you know if you see a
clearinghouse maybe there's a technology
solution that would be sort of more
participatory for for the network that
depends on that that clearinghouse and
that's kind of where we have certainly
some of our focus it's good to know that
there are some clear use cases coming up
specifically around asset tracking
supply chain
you mentioned founder table you know
clearing houses that have certain amount
of you know tracking and reconciliation
to be done within say you know a
multi-party network or you know
something where you want to build trust
with a single source of truth so this is
you know this moves us into the the next
point mostly towards the towards the end
of the show around the challenges that
you have seen or the evolution that is
from here so you know you mentioned
aetherium kind of addressed some of the
the points you know within the Bitcoin
network and and came up with this
additional concept of smart contracts
also the the use cases have been
evolving as we speak
but what are some of the technology
challenges that you have seen in this
space and then we move into the
evolution of this beyond here I'd say
that the technology is compared to many
others relatively immature but I would
say that's not the main barrier of
adoption I think the difficulty in
adoption
especially in the enterprise context but
even in the public network context is
that people have to change their
behavior and then in the enterprise
context to really see the benefit they
have to redesign to some degree
how they do business and and that means
having a more collaborative relationship
with you know their partners suppliers
customers that you know that's what it
would really take to get a whole
consortium or you know network of
participants at the same blockchain
online and so that's a very complex
process and then there's there's
governance concerns as you know okay so
we're a consortium but do we need a
legal entity to check who everyone and
the consortium is even at the network
permissioning level at the you know at
the corporate level etc and who
maintains the infrastructure do we all
have to maintain the infrastructure etc
these sort of questions become quite
complex when you have you know really
more than one trading counterparty but
especially as you have more than ten as
some of the consortium do they do
the governor's question becomes a big
one and just you know getting the
understanding out there or what the
benefits are and what you know the
minimal changes to an enterprise's
business process to see those benefits
which are considerable nevertheless this
there's quite an education challenge in
getting people to think that way and we
do see the eating community overall in
this space in the next couple years this
is an interesting question yeah so the
etherium community is it's hard to put a
label on it I would say at the beginning
you know if you compare public if dear I
am to public Bitcoin public etherion
community is sort of a little bit more
positive frankly they're sort of less
crypto anarchist a little more
engineering minded you know embracing
the change of the protocol embracing you
know iteratively fixing problems were
you know Bitcoin has been locked in the
same debates for 12 18 months so I think
that's that's a big mentality difference
however I you know lots of the theory
and community is sort of a shadow
community and that many corporations use
the technology but don't make too many
public statements about it and so the
aggregate number of people who use
the technology may actually reflect sort
of a corporate mindset though the
loudest voices are again the public
network advocates if you will so it's
hard to exactly pin down who the who the
etherium user is but so the enterprise
etherion alliance of which block EPS is
a founding board member and I personally
sit on the Technical Working Group is
kind of encompassing the corporate side
of aetherium and we're well over a
hundred member companies and so it'll be
a vehicle for that voice to to speak and
have some future in the governance of
both the public theorem protocol and
kind of enterprise derivatives of it so
time will tell exactly all right
also a little bit of interest that you
know I have seen from people now on be
the cryptocurrency space just you know
before we wrap up on the etherium aspect
is now around the old coins in mostly
around the fact that you know the price
of Bitcoin and and ether has been going
up what would you say about the whole
you know concept of all coins and tokens
I've also been reading about I CEOs the
initial coin offerings how are they
evolving in why I SEOs now yeah good
question so for the interested listener
I often look at coin market capcom which
sort of has a listing of most or all of
the the old coins basically an altcoin
as any blockchain currency besides
Bitcoin one one could debate whether or
not the theory accounts as an old coin
usually old coin means a Bitcoin
derivative but so that at any given
instant you can see the market cap of of
all of the crypto currencies on corn
market Capcom and you know it's a
fluctuating number there's a lot of
excitement frankly there probably a fair
number of speculators that are you know
moving those prices up and down and they
get an instant and kind of reflective of
the growth in the total market cap of
their currency is the trend toward icos
and so
what an IC o---- is is an offering of
tokens often on top of the etherium
protocol actually or otherwise so in
fact people write smart contracts which
take in the native aetherium token which
is called ether and then can issue sort
of sub tokens if you will so that's one
mechanism for to create an altcoin yeah
and so the IC o---- world has been has
become a vehicle to raise capital for
certain types of corporations or even
individuals that didn't exist before and
it's seemingly easier to get capital
from an IC o---- perspective then say
from traditional US venture capital so
it's an interesting phenomenon they're
happening all the time large amounts of
money are moving in short periods of
time you know you'll see fifteen million
dollars move in 30 minutes and so it
would be an interesting option for the
the less risk-averse startup founder to
explore as a way to get capital I would
caution any of the listeners against an
IC o---- both from their sort of unclear
legal territory and from a risk
perspective if if you succeed and are
ending up of handling quite a lot of
digital currency that's a sort of heavy
task from a security perspective so it
is nevertheless very interesting I would
say it's it's disrupting the traditional
venture model and we'll see sort of if
the current wave of icos is a to the
degree to which is a bubble or if it's a
sustaining trend interesting the way the
the token market has just adopted
challenging a lot of existing mechanisms
to to raise money it has been really
good akhirin talking to you about
various aspects of the blockchain world
starting from the history the evolution
the crypto anarchist thought process
that went in in in Bitcoin and then how
you know the industry itself has
embraced and and and started looking at
it from an enterprise software
development perspective in you know the
different types of use cases that are
coming up for blockchains
to be used in for developers you
actually gave a lot of context around
how to develop smart contracts or look
at solidity as the language in various
tools involved I believe that there's
there's a lot of follow up on how these
smart contracts can be used as a new
development paradigm for writing
transactions and in developing on top of
the etherium platform hopefully you know
the the listeners were excited about the
technology and we'll all go download our
developer edition lock up studnet and
otherwise enjoy their days awesome yeah
and where can people find more about you
and reach out myself personally that's a
good question actually I no longer have
a personal blog I do have a Twitter @k
James Levin jmes lu b IM you can also
try to connect with me on LinkedIn Kiran
kie re M James Lepine sure I remember to
put that link on the notes thanks so
much for joining us today Kevin thanks -
sure
this is Kishore partyi for software
engineering video thank you for
listening
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com
you can also email us at team @ SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
SU radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening